Guide to UE Radio Broadcasts and Film Records 1941-2002 UE.8.2
ULS Archives & Special Collections
UE Radio Broadcasts and Film Records
1941-2002
ULS Archives & Special Collections
United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America
UE.8.2
25.85 Linear Feet (27 boxes and 121 film reels)
This subgroup of the Education and Publicity Department Record Group contains correspondence, scripts, film, tapes, and other non-print media produced by the UE. The materials in this subgroup provide information on labor issues and UE conventions, in addition to an overview of how the UE interacted with the public and union members through film and radio programming.
History
The United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America (UE) Education Department is designed to educate members and workers about the union and labor issues. In addition to producing several publications throughout the year, the Education Department is responsible for the creation of informational films. In the past, the department produced radio programs that provided commentary on world events and labor issues. These programs were successful but, like many of the union's efforts during the 1950s, fell victim to budget cuts as the UE battled the CIO's International Union of Electrical Workers (IUE) for members.
Film was also acquired by the Research Department of the UE. Informational film produced by other unions and organizations about union committees and labor issues were kept for educational and research purposes. Footage of UE National Conventions and local events were also maintained by the union for future reference.
Scope and Content Notes
This subgroup of the Education and Publicity Department Record Group contains correspondence, scripts, film, tapes, and other non-print media produced by the UE. These may include locally produced items that the national office collected for research or national office productions. The materials in this subgroup provide an overview of how the UE interacted with the public and union members through film and radio programming. Film and video regarding labor issues such as sexism, automation, and workers rights indicate how the UE informed union members of problems they were facing. Audio reels and videos also record activity at several UE National Conventions.
There is a lot of content overlap between formats and series in this subgroup. Several film shorts, such as "Free Riding Rufus," "Keeping Up with the Van Jones," and "Sister UE Goes to Washington" are present in both U-Matic and reel to reel formats. Film and audio regarding Arthur Gaeth is found in the film and audio series.
Materials regarding renowned radio journalist Arthur Gaeth are processed to the folder level, otherwise material is processed to the series and box levels.
Arrangement
This subgroup has been divided into five series as follows:
Series 8.2.1. Arthur Gaeth Collection
Series 8.2.2. Other Radio Programs and Scripts
Series 8.2.3. Audio
Series 8.2.4. Film
Series 8.2.5. Slides
Access Restrictions
The records of the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America are closed for a period of twenty-five years after their creation.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America in 1986, 1997, and 2004.
Previous Citation
UE Radio Broadcasts and Film Records, 1941-2002, UE.8.2, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Red Channels: The Report of Communist Influence in Radio and Television can be found at the Hillman Library, University of Pittsburgh, call number HE8698 .A512.
Broadcasters; Videocassettes; Labor; Radio scripts; Educational videos; Labor unions and radio -- United States; Radio programs -- United States; Radio broadcasters -- United States; Radio broadcasting -- United States; American Broadcasting Company; Gaeth, Arthur; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America. Education Department; United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America. Publicity Department; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America. Research Department; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America
- Arthur Gaeth Collection, 8.2.1.
  Scope and Contents note
  Arthur Gaeth was born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, in 1906. He became a reporter well known to radio listeners for his liberal views on world events. Gaeth was one of two American reporters covering the execution of Nazi war criminals at Nuremberg and was the first reporter to broadcast from a hearing of the United States Senate. In 1947, Gaeth began to broadcast for the UE on the American Broadcasting Company (ABC) network. In addition, Gaeth also participated in lectures and submitted articles for publication. In January 1950, the UE could no longer afford to sponsor Gaeth's radio program due to their battle with their emerging CIO counterpart, the IUE. By June of the same year, he was denounced as a Communist in Red Channels: The Report of Communist Influence in Radio and Television and subsequently blacklisted within the entertainment industry.
  This series contains materials on the radio program On the Air with Arthur Gaeth, which was supported by the UE. Included are numerous files of correspondence by both UE and non-UE members requesting information on Gaeth or program scripts. In addition to correspondence, there are also several lists of stations that carried the Gaeth program during the late 1940s. Original and copied scripts of the Gaeth program from 1947-1950 discuss the American economy, labor union news, and foreign affairs, among other topics. Finally, the collection contains a short biography of Gaeth, printed broadcasts from 1947 to 1950, sample radio spots, and releases pertaining to the program. Audio of Gaeth can be found in Series 8-2-3 and film regarding Gaeth can be found in Series 8-2-4.
  - Biography, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Within the UE, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 02-08)
  - Correspondence Outside the UE, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 09-15)
  - List of ABC Stations, July 3, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - List of Newspapers where Ads are to be Placed, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - List of Stations Carrying UE Program, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Original Scripts, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Printed Broadcasts, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Releases: Gaeth Tour, July 3, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Releases: Labor Press, New Network, April 9, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Releases: Papers and All UE, New Live Stations, December 26, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Sample Letter for Community Use, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Sample Radio Spots (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Sample Spot Radio Announcement, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Scripts, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 29-31)
- Other Radio Programs and Scripts, 8.2.2.
  This series contains materials regarding various UE radio programs, excluding that of Arthur Gaeth. Scripts for the UE shows Report from Washington and News of Labor are represented as well as scripts from locally produced shows in Erie, Pittsburgh, Dayton, Schenectady, Johnstown, and Sunbury. Scripts used for television spots and UE produced movies are also present in this series. Many of these scripts contain information on local troubles and events, in addition to national union and labor issues. Correspondence regarding the union's search for radio stations to broadcast shows and requests for scripts are present as well.
  - "Report from Washington," "News of Labor," and Other Radio Scripts, 1950s (Box 2)
  - "Report from Washington" Scripts, 1953-1956 (Box 3)
  - Movie and radio scripts, local publications (Box 4)
  - Scripts from Erie, Pittsburgh, Dayton, Schenectady, Johnstown, and Sunbury (Box 5)
  - Local Television and Radio Scripts (Box 6)
  - Radio Scripts (Box 7)
  - Correspondence Regarding Broadcasts (Box 8)
- Audio, 8.2.3.
  The reels in this series contain audio recordings of various UE programs and presentations. Included are tapes of Arthur Gaeth radio programs, UE National Convention speeches, and informational programs on labor issues. A variety of other radio programs were recorded to preserve interviews with a variety of UE and labor leaders for future research. The names of these programs are not known due to a lack of identification on the boxes. Many of the reels are not labeled and have not been subsequently identified.
  - Audio Reels (Box 9-11)
  - Audio Reels of Radio Programs (Box 12)
  - Audio Cassettes (Box 13)
- Film, 8.2.4.
  This series contains short films, news, and convention footage regarding the UE. These include VHS, U-Matic, and reel to reel UE and locally produced films. The film in this series has been arranged by format and contains a variety of subject matter. Many of the reels contain short films on labor issues such as automation, while many of the VHS and U-Matic cassettes contain footage from UE National Conventions, Labor Party events, and local productions. Some of the short films exist in U-Matic and reel to reel formats. Inventories of the reel to reel, VHS, and U-Matic films exist and are accessible at the Archives Service Center. Several boxes of material from the UE local at the Westinghouse plant in East Pittsburgh are included in this series as well. These boxes contain film concerning specific events of the local.
  - VHS and U-Matic Cassettes (Box 14)
    - PTP Workers- Raw Footage, VHS, 1995; 1.
    - We Can Do It at PTP, VHS, 2-3.
    - March Against Police Brutality, Pittsburgh, VHS, 1996; 4.
    - Cox Creek- Free Forum in Baltimore, VHS, 1989; 5.
    - Convention Video- Local Interviews #3, VHS, 1994; 6.
    - Convention Video- Rally Interviews, VHS, 1994; 7.
    - UE History- Slides, VHS, 8.
    - UE History- Statements for History, VHS, 9.
    - Global Economy Workshop Part 1, VHS, 10.
    - IATSE Exposed, VHS, 11.
    - UE+IUGA=A Good Contract!, VHS, 12-13.
    - 50th Anniversary Slide Show, VHS, 14.
    - Woodmar: Our Future, VHS, 15-16.
    - Litton Corporate Campaign, VHS, 17.
    - Organizing Video- We Can Do It, Bob Kingsley, VHS, 18.
    - Pittsburgh Demonstrations- Heath Care Rally, Jobs With Justice on Channel 4 News, VHS, 1991; 19.
    - Pittsburgh Demonstrations- Heath Care Rally, Jobs With Justice on Channel 11 News, VHS, 1991; 20.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- Local 1421 Program and March, Compton, CA, VHS, 1995; 21.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- GE Plant and Gate Rally, VHS, 1988; 22.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- ACE Co. Rally, VHS, 1995; 23.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- JWJ WRB Hearing Workfare, Albany, NY, VHS, 1997; 24.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- GE Walkouts/Membership, Warner Theater, VHS, 1995; 25.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- Friction Demonstration, VHS, 1994; 26.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- Several Postal Workers Picket, California, VHS, 27.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- Rally at Federal Building, VHS, 1990; 28.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- Workers Rights/Bedford Leadership Meeting, VHS, 1991; 29.
    - Rallies & Demonstrations- Bob Kingsley- Generic Anti-NAFTA, VHS, 30.
    - GE/Parkersburg, VHS, 31.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video, Harold Lockhart, U-Matic, 1992; 32.
    - Miscellaneous Reel 3 of 3, U-Matic, 33.
    - Arthur Gaeth Reports, U-Matic, 34.
    - Women, U-Matic, 1953-1962; 35.
    - Women Conference Footage 2 of 2, U-Matic, 1953; 36.
  - VHS and U-Matic Cassettes (Box 15)
    - Fred Wright, U-Matic, 1.
    - Transferred UE Films: "Free Riding Rufus" "UE Goes to Press" "Keeping Up with the Van Jones" and "Sister UE Goes to Washington", U-Matic, 2.
    - Convention, Organizing Session, VHS, 1996; 3.
    - Convention, VHS, 1996; 4.
    - Labor Party Founding Convention, VHS, 1996; 5.
    - Michael Parenti Interview, Bernie Sanders Speech, Bertha Lujan Interview, VHS, 6.
    - ABQC/Steeltech/Ace Co/ELBEE CESCO Convention, VHS, 1995; 7.
    - Hugh Harley and Jim Kane Convention, VHS, 1995; 8.
    - Convention, Bob Wages, VHS, 1995; 9.
    - Convention, Rally Committee Meetings, VHS, 1995; 10.
    - Convention, Red Block Independent Political Action, VHS, 1995; 11.
    - Convention, QC Workshop, VHS, 1995; 12.
    - Parenti Interview, Beacon, Ron Daniels Speech, Friction, VHS, 13.
    - Ed Workshop/Erie, VHS, 1995; 14.
    - District 11 Council Meeting, VHS, June 1996; 15.
    - "Haiti Unchained", VHS, 16.
    - Labor Party Founding Convention Raw Tape, VHS, 1996; 17.
    - Labor Party Interview with Tony Mazocchi, VHS, 1996; 18.
    - "Labor Party Spot", VHS, 19.
    - Convention, Organizing Session 1 and 2, VHS, 1996; 20.
    - Convention, Tuesday Morning International Affairs, VHS, 1996; 21.
    - Convention, International Thursday Morning, VHS, 1996; 22.
    - Convention, Monday Organizing Session 2, VHS, 1996; 23.
    - "UE Goes to Press", VHS, 24.
    - Rallies and Demonstrations- Circuitwise at Woolsey Hall, VHS, 1989; 25.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - "Dub of Raw Footage", VHS, 26.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - "Erie Blitz Newscasts", VHS, 27.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - "Double R Charter Pittsburgh, PA", VHS, 1989; 28.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - "TULIP Meeting", VHS, 29.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - "Ft. Wayne PWOC8902 Rally (Original)", VHS, 1990; 30.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - "Plastek on UE Effort", VHS, 1990; 31.
  - VHS Cassettes (Box 16)
    - GE/Morristown "Recognition Song", VHS, 1988; 1.
    - Local 168 Message to Philadelphia Mayor Ed Rendall, VHS, 1994; 2.
    - Vote Count and Victory KGAN News Channel 2, VHS, 1996; 3.
    - Vote Count and Victory KGAN/Workers Memorial Service, VHS, 1996; 4.
    - Ohio Turnpike Public Sector Workers Interviews (Raw), VHS, 1995; 5.
    - Convention, Thursday Morning Speaker, VHS, 1990; 6.
    - Convention, Wednesday Afternoon Speaker, VHS, 1990; 7.
    - Convention, Thursday Afternoon Speaker, VHS, 1990; 8.
    - Convention, Opening Video, VHS, 1990; 9.
    - Convention, Organizing Report, VHS, 1990; 10.
    - Convention, Tuesday Morning Speaker, VHS, 1990; 11.
    - Convention, General Video Tape 1, VHS, 1990; 12.
    - Convention, Tuesday Afternoon Speaker, VHS, 1990; 13.
    - Convention, Wednesday Morning Speaker, VHS, 1990; 14.
    - Convention, GE Tape 3, VHS, 1990; 15.
    - Convention, Rally and Demonstration, VHS, 1990; 16.
    - Convention, Jan Pierce, VP CWA, VHS, 1991; 17.
    - Convention, Opening Monday, VHS, 1991; 18.
    - Convention, Rally, VHS, 1991; 19.
    - Convention, Opening: General President John Hovis, VHS, 1991; 20.
    - Convention, Jan Pierce, VHS, 1991; 21.
    - Convention, Organizing Session 1 and 2, VHS, 1991; 22.
    - Convention, Eugene Carol/Ann Wilson, VHS, 1991; 23.
    - Convention, Bernie Sanders, VHS, 1991; 24.
    - Convention, Admiral Eugene Carol Jr., VHS, 1991; 25.
    - Convention, Ann Wilson/Jobs with Peace, VHS, 1991; 26.
    - Convention, Interviews Part 4, VHS, 1988; 27.
    - Convention, Speech Part 1, VHS, 1988; 28.
    - Convention, Camacho, VHS, 1988; 29.
    - Convention, Pridgen/Camacho/Ramirez/Romero/Johnson, VHS, 1988; 30.
    - Convention, Proceedings Part 2, VHS, 1988; 31.
    - Convention, Chicago Convention Demonstration, VHS, 1989; 32.
    - Convention, Organizing Session, VHS, 1989; 33-34.
    - UE Conference Meeting in Beverly, MA, VHS, 1991; 35-36.
    - UE Conference A Quality Circle/Seminar Discussion UE Local 274, VHS, 1990; 37.
    - Steeltech Workers Rights and Public Accountability, VHS, 1995; 38.
    - Labor Relations Board Incident in Memphis, TN, VHS, 1993; 39.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - Chicago, VHS, 40.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - Erie Tad Tempo Demo, VHS, 41.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - "Double-R Presentation (Main Audio)", VHS, 42.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - Erie Blitz TV Spots, VHS, 1990; 43.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - Miami Valley (Ohio) Charter, VHS, 44.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - Interviews (Chicago or LA), VHS, 45.
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - Erie Newscasts, VHS, 1990; 46.
  - VHS Cassettes (Box 19)
    - District 11 Council, 8mm MP, June 22, 1996; 1-2.
    - Convention, Monday Morning Hightower Garvey Resolutions, VHS, 1997; 3.
    - Convention, Monday Resolutions and Rally Photograph, VHS, 1997; 4.
    - Convention, Organizing, VHS, 1997; 5.
    - Convention, Organizing/International, VHS, 1997; 6.
    - Convention, Tuesday Workshops, Racism, VHS, 1997; 7.
    - Convention, Unlabeled Tapes, VHS, 1997; 8-11.
    - Convention, Opening Workshop and Cutaways, VHS, 1997; 12.
    - Convention, VHS, 1999; 13.
    - Convention, Opening Photo, VHS, 1996; 14.
    - Convention, Opening with Hovis and Hargrove, VHS, 2000; 15.
    - Convention, Organizing Report, VHS, 2000; 16.
    - Convention, Rally and Ralph Nader, VHS, 2000; 17.
    - Convention, Organizing Report and Bourgeois, VHS, 2000; 18.
    - Convention, Monday Morning Aggressive Struggle, 506 Stewards, and Cutaways, VHS, 2000; 19.
    - Convention, Wednesday with Nader, Hill, and Roberts, VHS, 2000; 20.
    - Convention, International, VHS, 2000; 21.
    - Guastic and Labor Party Rallies, VHS, 1999; 22.
    - GE Contract Rally, VHS, 1997; 23.
    - Unfinished Business- Fight for Rights Under U.S. Labor Law, VHS, 24-26.
  - VHS Cassettes (Box 17)
    - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee - Charter Interviews, Cutaways, and RR Recognition, VHS, 1.
    - Convention, Local Interviews, VHS, 1994; 2.
    - Convention, Cutaway, VHS, 1994; 3.
    - Convention, Organizing Session, VHS, 1994; 4.
    - Convention, Workshop Dealing With Sexist Bosses Parts 1 and 2, VHS, 1995; 5.
    - Kerr Management Seminars Management Meeting Tapes 1-3, VHS, 1991; 6-8.
    - Political Action, VHS, 1995; 9.
    - Leadership Institute Bob Supansic, VHS, 1995; 10.
    - National Archives Video, VHS, 11.
    - Fairness at Friction, VHS, 1994; 12.
    - Friction Workers Solidarity Tour - Intro and Ending, VHS, 1995; 13.
    - Friction Workers Solidarity Tour - Worker to Company, 14.
    - Friction Workers Solidarity Tour - Chicago and Introduction, VHS, 1994; 15.
    - Friction Workers Solidarity Tour - Echlin Worker to Worker, 1994; 16.
    - Friction Workers Solidarity Tour - Trip 1 Virginia, Pennsylvania and Connecticut, VHS, 1994; 17.
    - Friction Workers Solidarity Tour - Worker to Company 2, VHS, 1994; 18.
    - Friction Workers Solidarity Tour - Worker to Worker, VHS, 1994; 19.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Cutaways, VHS, 20.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Coggeshall, VHS, 1992; 21.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Burkville GE Firing Story, VHS, 1992; 22.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Production Slides, VHS, 1992; 23.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Big Interview Tapes, VHS, 1992; 24.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Bert Greene/Corey Preston, VHS, 1992; 25.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Bobby Sprouse/Larry Stoops, VHS, 1992; 26.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Tape Ending 2, VHS, 1992; 27.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - "Which Side Are You On" Instrumental for Music, VHS, 1992; 28.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Frankfurt GE Sale Newscasts, VHS, 1992; 29.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Cutaways/Community Shots, VHS, 1992; 30.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video -- Video Cutaways Woodmar News, VHS, 1992; 31.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Nigel Andrews Slides, VHS, 1992; 32.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - 25th Hour Anti-Union Video, VHS, 33.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Actual Meeting Parkersburg Workers, VHS, 1992; 34.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - UE Rank and File Express, VHS, 1992; 35.
    - Parkersburg Woodmar Video - Dub Saturday Meeting Edit "Erie Express", VHS, 1992; 36.
    - What Every Worker Should Know #2 Cogs Victory, Detroit Strike, and Mouseland, VHS, 37.
  - VHS and U-Matic Cassettes (Box 18)
    - UE National Convention, U-Matic, 1957-1960; 1.
      - UE National Convention, 1958
    - Non-UE Productions, U-Matic, 2.
    - Miscellaneous Film, U-Matic, 3.
    - Women, VHS, 1953-1962; 4.
    - The Un-Americans, VHS, 5.
    - Keeping Up with the Van Jones, VHS, 6.
    - Free-Riding Rufus, VHS, 7.
    - Dirty Business, VHS, 8.
    - UE National Conventions, VHS, 1957-1960; 9.
    - Mouseland, VHS, 10.
    - Deadline for Action, VHS, 1946; 11.
    - "Drawing on Worker Culture" by Norman Wright, First Edit Rough Draft, VHS, 1994; 12.
    - Sister UE Goes to Washington, VHS, 13.
    - Non-UE Productions, VHS, 14-15.
    - Arthur Gaeth Reports, VHS, 1949; 16-17.
    - Fred Wright, VHS, 18.
    - Miscellaneous Film, VHS, 19.
    - UE Freudenberg, VHS, 2002; 20.
    - 63rd National Convention, Thursday, VHS, 1998; 21.
    - 63rd National Convention, Wednesday, VHS, 1998; 22-24.
    - 63rd National Convention, Tuesday Morning Sessions and Workshop Cutaways, VHS, 1998; 25.
    - 63rd National Convention, Monday Afternoon Organizing Report, VHS, 1998; 26-27.
    - 63rd National Convention, Monday Morning, VHS, 1998; 28-29.
    - 63rd National Convention, Sunday Morning Cutaways and Committee Meetings, VHS, 1998; 30.
  - UE Film Reels (Box 18, Reel 1-121)
    - Free-Riding Rufus (Box 18, Reel 10)
    - Keeping Up with the Van Jones (Box 18, Reel 14)
    - Time to Come Back, 1960 (Box 18, Reel 54)
    - Chug Chug (Box 18, Reel 89)
    - Shorter Work Week: One Answer to Automation, 1957 (Box 18, Reel 90)
    - The Myth, the Money, and the Many, 1959 (Box 18, Reel 94)
    - The Use of Stenofax Cartoons (Box 18, Reel 121)
    - William Sentner Story
    - Leading the Fight: A History of Action
      Scope and Content Notes
      A history of the United Radio and Machine Workers of America.
  - Westinghouse U-Matic Cassettes and Film Reels (Box 20-24)
- Slides, 8.2.5.
  The slide shows present in this series cover a variety of topics. Included are informational slides regarding the UE, labor issues, and government initiatives such as President Ronald Reagan's "Star Wars" program. Also present are photographic slides depicting UE National Conventions and District 11 meetings. These slides were used during presentations by members of the UE.
  - UE Slide Shows (Box 25-27)